{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>This man\u2019s efforts at social climbing included buying Hughenden Manor and marrying the</em> <em>widow of Wyndham Lewis.</em> After Robert Peel denied this man a cabinet seat, he became the leader of the Young England group. As prime minister, this author of the novels <em>Coningsby</em> and <em>Vivian Grey</em> introduced a bill to make Queen Victoria \u201cEmpress of India.\u201d This Conservative was the rival of William Gladstone. For 10 points, name this prime minister of Jewish descent.", "answer": "Benjamin <b><u>Disraeli</u></b> [or First Earl of <b><u>Beaconsfield</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>The Daily Mirror claimed Zaharie Shah, an employee of one of these businesses, had a</em> <em>suspicious computer program</em>. One of these businesses has headquarters at a location named for Sultan Abdul Aziz Shah in Subang. An employee of one of these businesses searched for information about \"doors and their security provisions\" before committing suicide by crashing into a mountain. For 10 points, name this kind of company exemplified by Germanwings.", "answer": "<b><u>airlines</u></b> [accept answers referring to <b><u>flight</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This man's longtime assistant and heir was Clyde Tolson</em>. This man claimed personal responsibility for the downfall of Alvin \"Creepy\" Karpis. After he died in 1972, his personal files containing incriminating information on many Presidents were destroyed. In 1956, this man's organization began the CO-INTELPRO program that targeted Communists and Black Panthers. For 10 points, name this first Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation.", "answer": "John Edgar <b><u>Hoover</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>The Trinovantes were recruited by this person to help battle an army led by Petillius Cerialis.</em> This leader destroyed the city of Camulodunum before being defeated by Gaius Suetonius Paulinus. The leader of the Iceni people, this person was married to Prasutagus until he died, after which she led an army to crush the Roman Ninth Legion. For 10 points, name this Celtic queen who rose up against Roman rule in 60 AD.", "answer": "<b><u>Boudicca</u></b> [or <b><u>Boadicea</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "VP"}, {"question": "<em>This work\u2019s third chapter claims that German philosophers saw the French Revolution as</em> <em>\u201ctrue human Will.\u201d</em> This work\u2019s second chapter calls for \u201cFree education for all children in public schools\u201d after calling for \u201cAbolition of the family!\u201d It begins \u201cA specter is haunting Europe,\u201d and claims that \u201cthe history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles.\u201d For 10 points, name this 1848 pamphlet co-authored by Friedrich Engels and Karl Marx.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Communist Manifesto</u></b></em> [or <em><b><u>Manifesto of the Communist Party</u></b></em> or <em><b><u>Manifest der</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Kommunistischen Partei</u></b></em>]  {I}", "metadata": "SH"}, {"question": "<em>Book 2 of Herodotus's</em> Histories<em> notes that \"other spices except frankincense\" were used</em> <em>during this process.</em> The object central to this process is dried with natron for seventy days. This process uses four canopic jars that represent the cardinal directions. The brain was removed through the nose during this process, which also requires wrapping the body with long strands of linen. For 10 points, identify this process used by Ancient Egyptians to preserve the dead.", "answer": "Egyptian <b><u>mummification</u></b> [accept word forms; prompt on <b><u>embalming</u></b> and other equivalent answers that do not specifically refer to a mummy]  {I}", "metadata": "KG"}, {"question": "<em>This composer\u2019s namesake songbook features a ballad which asks \u201call goodly sport, for my</em> <em>comfort, who shall me let?\u201d</em> This composer of\u201cPastime With Good Company\u201d employed choirmaster William Cornish, and his daughter gave Thomas Tallis a monopoly on music printing. According to popular legend, he wrote \u201cGreensleeves\u201d for his second wife. For 10 points, name this composer and English monarch who married and beheaded Anne Boleyn.", "answer": "King <b><u>Henry VIII</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em>Joseph Pulitzer offered a reward for information about this man's huckster father, Bill</em>. This man's estate is named for the Dutch word for \"lookout\" and is named Kykuit (<b>pr. KIE-quit</b>). Along with Henry Flagler and several investors, he led the \"Cleveland Conquest\" to take out business competitors. This man referred to company critic and muckraker Ida Tarbell as \"Miss Tarbarrel.\" For 10 points, name this patriarch of a wealthy family who founded the Standard Oil Company.", "answer": "John Davison <b><u>Rockefeller</u></b> Sr.  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This initiative directly caused the formation of Lake Chagan.</em> This project conducted tests at an area known as the \"Polygon.\" The \"Third Idea\" of this program was largely derived from a rival program's Teller-Ulam configuration. This program benefited greatly from information provided by Klaus Fuchs and the Rosenbergs. For 10 points, identify this project that produced Tsar Bomba, whose detonation produced the strongest man-made explosion in history.", "answer": "<b><u>Soviet nuclear</u></b> program [or <b><u>Soviet atomic</u></b> bomb program; accept <b><u>Russian</u></b> in place of \"Soviet\"]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This poem was believed to be a history until a fire in the Cotton library led to a second look at</em> <em>the Nowell Codex.</em> Clues to the proper date range of its composition include a raid on the Frisians and frequent references to \"Geats\" and \"Geatland\" in what's now Sweden. In this poem, attacks on the mead hall of Heorot lead to a plea for aid from King Hrothgar. For 10 points, name this poem in which a dragon and the monster Grendel are slain by the title hero, an Old English epic.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Beowulf</u></b></em>", "metadata": "MJ"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man competed in the North Channel Naval Duel against the</em> Drake<em> while commanding the</em> <em>Ranger</em>. After being denied command of the <em>America</em>, this native Scot entered the service of Catherine the Great. In a battle against the <em>Countess of Scarborough</em> and <em>Serapis</em>, this man exclaimed, \u201cI have not yet begun to fight!\u201d For 10 points, name this captain of the <em>Bonhomme</em> <em>Richard</em>, a naval hero of the American Revolution.", "answer": "John Paul <b><u>Jones</u></b> [or John <b><u>Paul</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This dynasty won the battle of Tolbiac against the Alemanni.</em> Fredegar claims that the kings of this dynasty descended from a mythical sea creature called the Quinotaur. Much of the history of this dynasty survives only through the writing of Gregory of Tours. This dynasty ended when Pope Zachary deposed Childeric III. Saint Remigius baptized this dynasty\u2019s founder Clovis I. For 10 points, name this Frankish dynasty that preceded the Carolingian dynasty.", "answer": "<b><u>Merovingian</u></b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Charles Lightoller threatened some people trying to leave from this event because they weren't</em> <em>English.</em> During this event, a band is said to have played \"Nearer, My God, to Thee.\" J. Bruce Ismay controversially fled this event early, while Margaret Brown stayed to help. This disaster for the White Star Line occurred despite warnings from the SS <em>Californian</em> about dangerous icebergs. For 10 points, identify this 1912 event in which a supposedly unsinkable ship capsized.", "answer": "sinking of the RMS <em><b><u>Titanic</u> </b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This leader is cast as a \"Jacobin\" in a history by C. L. R. James.</em> This man became the most prominent leader of an event which began after a ceremony at Bois Caiman conducted by Dutty Boukman. This man fought the War of Knives with Andre Rigaud, and he was eventually captured by Charles Leclerc. This man's officers included future emperors Henri-Christophe and Jean-Jacques Dessalines. For 10 points, name this leader of the Haitian Revolution.", "answer": "Toussaint L'<b><u>Ouverture</u></b> [or Francois Dominique Toussaint L'<b><u>Ouverture</u></b>; or Toussaint <b><u>Breda</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man was opposed by \u201cSnow White and the six dwarfs\u201d and was nicknamed \u201cPepsi-Cola</em> <em>kid.\u201d</em> Millard Tydings investigated this man\u2019s claims, which sparked Margaret Chase Smith\u2019s \u201cDeclaration of Conscience\u201d speech. This person was finally brought down after Joseph Welch asked him if he had \u201cno sense of decency\u201d during hearings with the U.S. Army. For 10 points, name this man nicknamed \u201cTail Gunner,\u201d a Senator who helped fuel the Red Scare in the 1950s.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>McCarthy</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The winner of the 2012 Arthur Ashe Courage Award, this coach was named the Naismith</em> <em>Coach of the Century in 2000</em>. Candace Parker made a landmark slam dunk while playing for this coach, who was diagnosed with early-onset Alzheimer's disease in 2011. For 10 points, name this longtime coach of the University of Tennessee women\u2019s basketball team who is the winningest coach in the history of NCAA basketball.", "answer": "Pat <b><u>Summitt</u></b> [or Patricia <b><u>Head</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Members of this party include a governor who ordered the burning of railroad bridges</u></b></em> <em><b><u>leading to Baltimore.</u></b></em><b><u> Thomas Holliday Hicks was a member of this party, which was</u></b> <b><u>formed from the Order of the Star-Spangled (+)</u> Banner. MillardFillmore carried only Maryland as its 1856 Presidential candidate. This party advocated for a 25-year</b> (*) residency requirement for citizenship as part of its nativist platform. For 10 points, what anti-Catholic and anti-immigrant third party took its colloquial name from its members' responses when asked about its activities?", "answer": "<b><u>Know-Nothing</u></b> Party [or Native <b><u>American</u></b> Party]  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Independently of James Lind, this man discovered that sauerkraut could prevent scurvy.</u> </b></em><b><u>This man replaced Alexander Dalrymple as the leader of a voyage to observe a transit of</u></b> <b><u>Venus. During that voyage, this man stopped in \"Stingray (+)</u>Harbor,\" where Daniel Solander and Joseph Banks collected so many species that it was renamed (*)</b> \"Botany Bay.\" This commander of the <em>Endeavor</em> proved that New Zealand was composed of two islands. For 10 points, name this British explorer whose three eighteenth-century voyages mapped much of the Pacific Ocean.", "answer": "James <b><u>Cook</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man joked \"Well, God has arrived\" when his friend Ludwig Wittgenstein came to</u></b></em> <em><b><u>teach at his university.</u></b></em><b><u> This philandering husband of dancer Lydia Lopokova, a non-</u><u>philosopher who discussed philosophy with the Bloomsbury Group, proposed the</u></b> <b><u>underlying assumptions that Alvin (+)</u>Hansen used to make the IS/LM model. This man argued that demands for heavy reparations would cripple (*)</b> Germany's economy in <em>The</em> <em>Economic Consequences of the Peace.</em> For 10 points, name this Cambridge economist whose <em>General Theory</em> argued for government deficit spending during recessions.", "answer": "John Maynard <b><u>Keynes</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>According to lore, a cannonball attacking this institution went right through a portrait of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>George II.</u> </b></em><b><u>A siege during the American Revolution damaged this place's Nassau Hall in</u></b> <b><u>January 1777. Theologian Jonathan Edwards briefly served as president of this (+)</u> institution while it was still named merely for the stateit's located in. This school traded a cannon back and forth with its historic rival (*)</b> Rutgers in the 19th century, before its dining societies developed into the current \"eating clubs.\" For 10 points, name this Ivy League university located in New Jersey.", "answer": "<b><u>Princeton</u></b> University [prompt on <b><u>College of New Jersey</u></b>, accept \u201c<b><u>Nassau Hall</u></b>\u201d before mention]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>One ruler of this name was replaced by Amadeo I after abdicating</u></b></em><b><u>. A ruler of this name</u></b> <b><u>abdicated after losing the Battle of Alcolea to Juan Prim and Francisco Serrano. That ruler</u></b> <b><u>succeeded her father Ferdinand VII and fought supporters of her (+)</u>uncle in the Carlist Wars. Another queen with this name forced the surrender of Muhammad XII and united the (*)</b> crowns of Castile and Aragon through marriage. For 10 points, give this name common to two Spanish queens, the first of whom completed the Reconquista along with her husband Ferdinand.", "answer": "<b><u>Isabel</u></b>la  {I}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This leader's police opened fire on protesters at the Turkman Gate in an incident</u></b></em> <em><b><u>investigated by the Shah Commission.</u></b></em><b><u> Slogans such as \"Elect a Government That Works\"</u></b> <b><u>and \"Eradicate Poverty!\" were used by this leader with a lifelong white streak of</u> (+)hair</b>. <b>This leader put a relative in charge of aslum clearance and forced sterilization program, ruled by decree during the Emergency period, and ordered Operation (*)</b> Blue Star, a raid on the Golden Temple. For 10 points, name this Prime Minister of India who was assassinated by Sikh bodyguards, the daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru.", "answer": "<b><u>I</u></b>ndira <b><u>Gandhi</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Gandhi</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Cecil Morgan aided a \"squad\" named for this substance which aimed to impeach populist</u></b></em> <em><b><u>governor Huey Long.</u></b></em><b><u> A reaction involving this substance destroyed the Braamfontein train</u></b> <b><u>station in South Africa in 1887. Adsorbents such as diatomaceous earth are part of the</u></b> <b><u>mixture that composes this (+)</u>substance and allows for its safe transport. The casualties made possible by this substance inspired its inventor to write</b> (+) awards into his will which are given out in Oslo and Stockholm yearly. For 10 points, name this nitroglycerin-based solid devised by Alfred Nobel, an explosive often packed into \"sticks\".", "answer": "<b><u>dynamite</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A proposed extension of this system in the Vieux Carre (</u></b><u>pr. VYUH cah-RAY</u><b><u>) area was the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>subject of a controversy called the \"Second Battle of New Orleans.\"</u></b></em><b><u> The financial viability of</u></b> <b><u>this system was assessed by the Clay Committee. This system was planned in the Yellow</u></b> <b><u>Book, and it realized the goals proposed in the Pershing Map. Lady Bird Johnson</u></b> <b><u>campaigned for a (+)</u> \"Beautification Act\" affecting this system. A 1919 army convoy trip and the (*)</b> Autobahn inspired President Eisenhower to champion the creation of this system. For 10 points, name this system of large roads across the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>interstate</u></b> highway system [prompt on \u201chighways\u201d or \u201cfreeways\u201d prompt on \"roads\" or equivalents]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Oscar Colquitt settled a feud between Adina de Zavala and Clara Driscoll over control of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>this place.</u></b></em><b><u> This place was the last holdout of Manuel Cos before his surrender to Edward</u></b> <b><u>Burleson following the Siege of Bexar</u></b><u> (pr. bay-ar)</u><b><u>. After James Neill left, William (+)</u> Travis and Jim Bowie shared control of this site, whose defense was compared by Anson Jones to (*) </b>that \"of the pass of Thermopylae.\" For 10 points, around two hundred defenders were killed during an 1836 siege of what San Antonio mission, leading to cries to \"Remember\" it?", "answer": "the <b><u>Alamo</u></b> [or Mission <b><u>San Antonio de Valero</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>San Antonio</u></b> before it is read]  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}], "bonuses": []}